All right, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף Daf is ק״יא, Kuf-Yud-Aleph,
111, plus. Okay, so we pick up at the bottom of ק״י
עמוד ב׳ Kuf-Yud Amud Bet and not the bottom unfortunately, close to
the bottom, and we are going through this whole discussion about whether
a woman who was married as a חרשת chereshet and which is
only דרבנן derabbanan and now there's a יבום yibbum obligation, whether she
can do יבום, yibbum, or normally a חרשת chereshet could not do
יבום yibbum because besides the בר דעת bar-da'as issue she can't speak,
but will we allow it because her marriage was only דרבנן, derabbanan,
her marriage was as a חרשת chereshet and רב Rav had said
we would allow her to do יבום, yibbum, I think it was
רב, Rav, רבא, Rava, excuse me, and we're bringing evidence from all
this whole משנה Mishna at the beginning of the next פרק perek
that deals with חרשת chereshet in various situations and consistently assumes that
she cannot do יבום, yibbum, the גמרא Gemara tried to assert that
those were cases where she was married as a hearing person, but
through working through the משנה Mishna it was clear that some of
the cases at the end were cases where she clearly was a
חרשת chereshet from beginning to end and therefore it says that's therefore
clear pretty much that that's what the משנה Mishna is talking with
and that רבא Rava is incorrect, even when she was married as
a חרשת chereshet she cannot do חליצה. chalitza. So the rest of
this section of this discussion is just going to be re-proving it
from a different part of that משנה. Mishna. So let's take a
look.
So אשתק, ishtik, רבא Rava was silent, אתא לקמיה, Ata Lekamei, the
word is
אתא לקמיה, Ata Lekamei, it's pretty much across from the תוספות Tosafot
אתא לקמיה, Ata Lekamei, it's like I don't know thirty lines down
or something, אתא לקמיה דרב יוסף, Ata Lekamei de-Rav Yosef, when whoever
it was, he who was challenging רבא, Rava, I forget who
it was,
אביי, Abaye, that would have been a good guess, when אביי Abaye
came in front of רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, so רב יוסף Rav
Yosef said to him, מאי טעמא תסתרי מהא, Mai Taama Tostrei Me-ha,
why did you ask him from that section of the משנה Mishna
that we dealt with yesterday, דיכול לשנויי לך, de-yakhol leshanoye lakh, because
then he could tell you, אחיות חרשות מעיקרא, achayot cherashot me-ikara, the
section that was clear that it was about a woman who was
a חרשת chereshet from the beginning was a case of two sisters,
that maybe
he would concede, but נוכריות, nokhriyot, the section that really disproved his
position, which was dealing with women who aren't sisters, פקחות ואחר כך
נתחרשו, pikchot ve-achar nitcharshu, maybe again that was cases where they were
originally hearing, so you really haven't totally proved it, you proved a
section of the משנה Mishna was that they were חרשות cherashot but
not necessarily the section that was most relevant. אלא איבעי לך לאקשויי
מהא, Ella ibaya lakh le-akshoye me-ha,
you should have asked him from this section: שני אחים חרשים נשואים
שתי אחיות פקחות, shnei achim cherashim nesuim shtei achayot pikchot, two brothers
married to two sisters, and what we're going to, two brothers are
deaf, married to two sisters, and it's going to go through six
cases, it's really five cases because and it's going to say about
that either both brothers were חרשים cherashim or both sisters were חרשות,
cherashot, so you understand that no matter therefore what the other gender
was,
the marriages will both be דרבנן. derabbanan. Is that clear? Right? Two
brothers, two sisters, either both brothers are חרשים cherashim or both sisters
are חרשות, cherashot, so we're dealing with a דרבנן, derabbanan, both of
them are דרבנן derabbanan marriages. So let's list these six cases which
are really five.
שני אחים חרשים, shnei achim cherashim, two brothers that are deaf, נשואים
לשתי אחיות פקחות, nesuim lishtei achayot pikchot, married to two sisters, either
they are hearing, the sisters, או שתי אחיות חרשות, o shtei achayot
cherashot, or they are deaf,
או שתי אחיות אחת פקחת ואחת חרשת, o shtei achayot achat pikachat
ve-achat chereshet, or one is hearing and one is deaf, okay, so
that's three scenarios where both brothers are deaf. וכן שתי אחיות חרשות,
ve-chen shtei achayot cherashot, or two sisters that are deaf, נשואות לשני
אחים פקחים, nesuot lishnei achim pikchim, are married either to two hearing
brothers, או לשני אחים חרשים, o lishnei achim cherashim, or two brothers
that are deaf, או לשני אחים אחד פקח ואחד חרש, o lishnei
achim echad pikach ve-echad cheresh, one is hearing and one is deaf.
The reason I said it's six that are five is because when
both brothers and sisters are deaf, that was mentioned in both of
the lists.
Yeah, exactly. Anyway, doesn't matter. Either both brothers are deaf or both
sisters are deaf, so it's all קידושין דרבנן. kiddushin derabbanan. What's the
הלכה? halakha? הרי אלו פטורות מן החליצה ומן היבום, harei elu pturot
min hachalitza u-min hayibbum, so one of the brothers dies, the other
brother is exempt from חליצה chalitza and יבום. yibbum. Why? Because אחות
אשתו, achot ishto, right? Wife's sister. And it's all within the world
of נישואי חרש nissuei cheresh because everybody's dealing in the same universe
of the rabbinic marriages of חרשים, cherashim, so therefore it is within
that universe, it's אחות אשתו achot ishto and the woman walks away.
פטורות מן החליצה ומן היבום, pturot min hachalitza u-min hayibbum, ואם היו
נוכריות, ve-im hayu nokhriyot, but if they weren't sisters, יכניסו, yikhnesu, then
here you are, this person, ראובן Reuven has his obligation of יבום,
yibbum, but he, right? Because what, because one of the sides is
not, you know, I'm sorry, the sisters are not related to one
another. Okay, so basically what you've got, sisters are not related to
one another, that made a lot of sense. Okay, so basically what
you have is you have ראובן Reuven
and
שמעון. Shimon. Okay, so they're obviously brothers. Okay,
and if they're married, both of these are נשואי חרש, nisuei cheiresh,
okay, both, I don't know why I'm making the woman small, both
of these are cases of only דרבנן, derabanan, it's only a rabbinic
marriage, it's נשואי חרש, nisuei cheiresh, and one of them dies. Now
if they're sisters, they're all within the same universe of נשואי חרש,
nisuei cheiresh, so it's אחות אשה achot isha walks away. If they're
not sisters, he's got a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum or חליצה
chalitzah דרבנן derabanan within the world of the marriage of marriages of,
you know, one of them is is a is death. So he
has a מצוה mitzvah of, so so we'd say what you do
when you have a מצוה mitzvah of חליצה chalitzah of יבום yibum
דרבנן, derabanan, do יבום yibum or do חליצה. chalitzah. But he can't
do חליצה. chalitzah. Why can't he do חליצה? chalitzah?
Because some of these scenarios, the woman is a חרשת. chereshet. And
if the woman is a חרשת, chereshet, she can't do חליצה. chalitzah.
So חליצה chalitzah we're not going to discuss, we're only going to
discuss יבום, yibum, and then so let's take a look. So ואם
היו נכריות, ve'im hayu nochriyot, if they were not related, יכנסו, yichnesu,
then they can marry, then they can do יבום, yibum, ואם רצו
להוציא יוציאו, ve'im ratzu lehotzi yotziu, and if they want divorce they
can divorce. Now you should be saying, what do you mean they
can divorce? We said that a חרש cheiresh can't give a גט,
get, he's not a בר דעת, bar da'at, right? But since the
whole thing is only rabbinic, right, we allow a חרש cheiresh to
give a divorce within the rabbinic world. If a חרש cheiresh marries
a woman, then the same way the marriage was rabbinic, he can
give her a divorce. Right, this is the irony, right, that you
might not be able to do חליצה chalitzah when you're dealing with
the marriage of a חרשת, chereshet, but you can give a divorce
when you're in that world. Is everybody with me or have I
totally confused everyone?
I just forget why that is. I forget.
Because the line in the משנה mishna is כשם שכונס ברמיזה כך
מוציא ברמיזה. keshem shekoneis b'remiza kach motzi b'remiza. The same way the
rabbis allowed a חרש cheiresh to marry rabbinically, they allowed him to
divorce rabbinically. It all works within the closed rabbinic system. And the
same, so so here what we're saying is is that you have
this closed system of marriages of חרשים, chereshim, you know, one or
both of them are חרשים, chereshim, so he can do יבום, yibum,
and since that's all within this and since that's within this it's
only all rabbinic here, he can after he does יבום yibum give
her a גט. get. But the one thing we won't allow, ironically,
even though we're going to allow יבום yibum and a גט, get,
even though he's a חרש cheiresh to write a גט, get, we're
not going to allow חליצה. chalitzah. Because even though the whole thing
is within the rabbinic world of חרשים chereshim and of rabbinic, we're
not going to allow her to do חליצה, chalitzah, we're only going
to allow a case of יבום yibum and a גט. get.
I don't understand why.
Well, okay, the גמרא gemara never explains why, it just proves it.
Wait, let's just read the case. Hold on. So it says, so
it says ואם רצו להוציא יוציאו ve'im ratzu lehotzi yotziu and then
afterwards you can you can give a גט. get. היכי דמי, heichi
dami, what's the case? אילימא בפיקחין ובסוף נתחרשו, ilima b'pikchin uvesof nitcharshu,
if the marriages were first when they were hearing and then they
became deaf. מצי מפטרי? matzu miftari? Then they would never, then if
it's all, then you're on the דאורייתא de'oraita plane and then the
יבום yibum is a דאורייתא יבום de'oraita yibum and then a גט
get wouldn't be possible. והתנן, vehatnan, we talked in the משנה, mishna,
we'll skip the first five lines, the three words, which is which
is not relevant part of the משנה, mishna, נתחרש הוא או נשתטה
לא יוציא עולמית. nitcharesh hu o nishtata lo yotzi olamit.
If they, he married when he was well and then became deaf
or became a שוטה, shoteh, he can never divorce her. So if
we're allowing him to do יבום yibum and give a גט, get,
it must be that everybody was everybody was originally a חרש cheiresh
and we're only in the rabbinic world. ואלא לאו חרשין מעיקרא. ve'ela
lav chereshin me'ikara. ומדאינון חרשין מעיקרא, umide'inun chereshin me'ikara,
since the case by the men is that they were חרשין מעיקרא,
chereshin me'ikara, or else we would never let them write a גט,
get, אינהו נמי חרשות מעיקרא. inhu nami chereshot me'ikara. So obviously the
women are also, this is all the same case. וקתני, vekatani, so
all this is clear that it's all talking about that everything was
purely rabbinic. Nobody was ever hearing. Everybody was always deaf. וקתני אם
היו נכריות יכנסו vekatani im hayu nochriyot yichnesu and even so, all
we allow is יבום, yibum, יכנסו אין יחלצו לא, yichnesu in yachaltzu
lo, only יבום, yibum, not חליצה. chalitzah. תיובתא דרבה תיובתא, tiyuvta deRabba
tiyuvta, that is a complete contradiction of רבה. Rabba. So without going
through the whole thing we went through yesterday, we proved more directly
that in this case where it's clear that it's all rabbinic marriages,
that's clear, everybody was a חרש cheiresh to begin with and nevertheless
we do not allow the women to do חליצה. chalitzah. So that
proves, it's not clear why, right, we allow the man to do
יבום yibum and write a גט get even though a חרש cheiresh
normally can't write a גט, get, but because we're living within this
rabbinic world, but for some reason we still don't allow the woman
to do חליצה chalitzah and that is and that is the conclusion.
Yes.
And these two weren't sisters.
In in this second case, no, they're not. They're not. If they're
sisters then the other one walks away, then you just walk away.
But if they're not sisters you have to either do, you know,
you do יבום. yibum.
Does the the woman who was married whose husband passed away walks
away?
Exactly.
I know we're sort of skirting around but what I'm not quite
understanding is the גמרא's gemara view of the חרש. cheiresh.
Like meaning its hearing capability is lost, not like your mind went.
I understand. So let's hold that off. We're going to get to
a whole פרק perek called חרש, cheiresh, okay? So yes, but what's
clear here, and also because the גמרא, gemara, A, the גמרא gemara
allows for a חרש cheiresh to write a גט get but doesn't
allow for a שוטה shoteh to write a גט, get, you know,
in this case of where it's all rabbinic. B, the fact that
the גמרא gemara focuses on the problem here of the חרש cheiresh
as that he can't say or the חרשת chereshet that she can't
say the verses rather than that she's not a בר דעת. bar
da'at. The גמרא Gemara always sort of recognizes חרש Cheresh as more
of a בר דעת bar da'at than a שוטה. shotah. There's no
question about that. Okay. קטנה וחרשת. Katanah v'chereshet.
Now we're going to get to the fun part. Okay. So, the
משנה Mishnah says that if a man is married to a
קטנה Katanah and a חרשת, Chereshet, two wives,
should we use some colors?
All right, okay fine, we'll make them different colors. That's the קטנה,
Katanah, this is the חרשת. Chereshet.
A חרשת Chereshet is a גדולה? gedolah?
Is a גדולה, gedolah, and he's married to both of them, and
he dies. And he dies. Okay. So his brother here, his brother
here cannot do, as opposed to if they're both חרשות charashot or
both קטנות katanot where they're at the same level. It says he
does יבום yibbum or חליצה chalitzah with one of them and the
other one walks away, like in the normal case of a marriage,
right? A normal case of יבום yibbum with two wives. But because
they're different, they're both דרבנן, derabbanan, but they are of a different
quality, and we'll get to that in a minute, then you can't
assume what you did with one works with the other. So you
basically have to go ahead and do either יבום yibbum and חליצה
chalitzah with one and like the other with the other and the
גמרא's Gemara going to figure out what you have to do. But
the first point of departure is that just because he does יבום
yibbum or חליצה chalitzah with one, it doesn't deal with his obligation
and his זיקה zikah to the other. Now just so you know
that the גמרא Gemara is going to say is going to assume
and for the sake of our time and our whatever focus, I'm
not going to demonstrate how the גמרא Gemara knows this. The רש״י
Rashi at the bottom of the דף daf sort of demonstrates it
if you want to read it on your own time, but the
גמרא's Gemara going to assume in a few minutes that the nature
of the different types of דרבנן derabbanan marriages is that one of
them is considered to be a quasi-קידושין, kiddushin,
מקודשת ומשויירת, mekudeshet umshuyeret, there's a remnant, it's not full, it's quasi-קידושין.
kiddushin. And the other is going to be considered a ספק קידושין,
safek kiddushin, מקודשת ואינה מקודשת, mekudeshet v'einah mekudeshet, right? So is it
fifty percent or is it a hundred percent or zero? Okay. ספק
safek is a hundred percent or zero, or משויירת meshuyeret fifty percent.
So we'll worry about that in a minute, but that's what the
גמרא's Gemara going to assume that there's a different type of a
קידושין kiddushin with one as opposed to the other.
And then he'll get
older and it'll be full. Okay, so you're assuming which way it's
going to go. The גמרא Gemara doesn't know which way it's going
to go. Okay, let's take a look. So, אמר רב נחמן, Amar
Rav Nachman, so רב נחמן Rav Nachman said, אשכחתי
לרב אדא בר אהבה ולרב חנא חתניה דחנה Ashkachtei l'Rav Adda bar
Ahava u'l'Rav Chana chasneih d'Chana Rav
Adda bar Ahava and Rav Chana his son-in-law, דיתבי קמי כוורי וקבעי
כוותא d'yasvi kamei kavrei v'kav’ei kavasah they were sitting and doing something,
רש״י Rashi says it means they were asking questions to one another,
okay, בשוקא דפומבדיתא, b'shuka d'Pumbedita, in the marketplace of Pumbedita. ואמרי, V'amri,
and they said, חזיתן קטנה וחרשת אין ביאת אחת מהן פוטרת צרתה
hazitan katanah v'chereshet ein biat achat mehen poteret tzaratah a קטנה katanah
and חרשת, chereshet, having doing יבום yibbum with one does not get
the other one off. הני מילי
דנפלו ליה מאח פקח Hanei milei d'naflu leih m'ach pike'ach are we
talking about how were they who are they married to, was it
a case that they were married to his brother who was a
hearing adult brother
and therefore we don't know which of these two women is the
more weighty marriage and what's the ספק. safek. Now this becomes very
strange how he frames the ספק. safek. דלא ידעינן אי בקטנה ניחא
ליה d'lo yadeinan ei b'katanah nicha leih would did the brother rather
be married, if he had to choose between which wife, would he
rather be married to the minor, why? אי בחרשת ניחא ליה ei
b'chereshet nicha leih or would he rather be married to his deaf
wife? אי בקטנה ניחא ליה ei b'katanah nicha leih maybe he'd rather
be married to his minor wife דאתיא לכלל דעה, d'asya l'klal de'ah,
eventually she would become an adult and she'd be a and therefore
you know and he'd be more with
somebody more that he could relate to. אי בחרשת ניחא ליה ei
b'chereshet nicha leih or maybe he'd rather be married right now to
the adult even though she was deaf, דגדולה היא d'gedolah hi because
she's an adult, ובת ביאה היא u'vat bi'ah hi and he can
be having sex with her. Okay, so therefore that's why we don't
know which one he'd prefer. Now of course it's so funny that
he frames the whole thing, who cares what he would prefer? This
is a legal question, right? Why don't you ask him? Who's your
favorite wife, רחל או לאה? Rachel o Leah? Right. So no, I
mean why so
it's very strange that it frames it as who would he prefer.
Let's maybe slightly reframe it as you know which one would הלכה
halachah recognize as the more עיקר ikkar marriage because of an assumption
of you know what about what men would normally prefer. Okay, it's
very funny to frame it in terms of his personal assumption. But
anyway, maybe that's the case when he's married to an adult you
know a hearing adult and therefore we can't determine which one is
the more עיקר ikkar marriage. אבל נפלה מאחיו חרש, Aval nefla m'achiv
cheresh, but let's say they were these two women were both married
to a חרש, cheresh, a deaf person, then in that case maybe
we'd say ודאי בחרשת ניחא ליה. vadai b'chereshet nicha leih. Maybe in
that case we'd say you have a חרש cheresh married a deaf
person married to a minor and to an adult deaf woman. So
then maybe we'd say הלכה halachah would recognize his marriage to the
adult deaf woman as the עיקר ikkar marriage, okay, as having more
weight, דבת ביאה היא. d'vat bi'ah hi. I'm sorry, I skipped a
word. Yeah, דבת ביאה היא, devas biah hi,
yes, because she can have sex with her right now, ובת מיניה
היא, u-vas minei hi, and she's similar to him, you know that
they're both deaf. So maybe when they're married to a חרש, cheresh,
we should take it for granted that the חרש cheresh marriage to
the חרשת chereshet is assumed to have more weight.
Wait, נפלו משני אחי חרש naflu mi-shnei achi cheresh means that she-
these two women had been married to a חרש cheresh and he
and he died. אה, נפלו
מרשותו, Ah,
naflu
me-reshuso,
they fell from, right, Reuven. Okay. Okay, ואמינא להו אנא, va-amina lehu
ana, I said to them, אפילו נפלו לו מאחיו חרש נמי מספקא
לי. afilu naflu lo me-achiv cheresh nami mesapka lei. No,
even if the man they were married to was a חרש, cheresh,
we don't know. And it's not a question of what he would
prefer or maybe even what men would prefer. There's a technical legal
question here about the difference between נישואי חרש nisuei cheresh and נישואי
קטנה nisuei ktana and it has nothing to do with what the
status story of the man is. And now we're going to turn
our attention to that question about the fact that נישואי חרשת nisuei
chereshet and נישואי קטנה nisuei ktana are both rabbinic but operating at
different levels. Let's take a look. Okay. So
now, כיצד תקנתם? keitzad takanasam? How do you deal with this situation?
Now, how do you deal with it? So let's start to figure
out how we would deal with it. Okay. Let's say, I don't
know, do ייבום yibum with the חרשת chereshet and do חליצה chalitza
with the קטנה. ktana. Okay, wait till the קטנה ktana grows up,
assuming the קטנה ktana can do חליצה chalitza because remember a חרשת
chereshet cannot do, cannot do חליצה. chalitza.
Reuven and Shimon are both חרשים, chershim, right? Yeah, yeah.
Okay. So so what are we going to do? So חרשת chereshet
cannot do חליצה. chalitza. Remember that? Yeah. Okay. So קטנה ktana can
do חליצה chalitza either as a קטנה ktana or when she grows
up, depending on how we פסקן. pasken. All right. So do קטנה,
ktana, do חליצה chalitza with a קטנה ktana and ייבום yibum with
the חרשת. chereshet. That'll be a way of solving the situation. Only
a bit of a problem, which is is that after you've done
חליצה chalitza with a קטנה, ktana, right,
the ייבום yibum with the חרשת chereshet is going to be a
case where
if the relationship, right, if the קטנה ktana sort of relationship is
the more weighty one, put it that way, then he is done
with the ייבום yibum idea after he's done חליצה chalitza with the
קטנה. ktana. And if he's done with all ייבום yibum idea, then
he can't do ייבום, yibum, right? So it doesn't, right, it doesn't
allow for ייבום yibum to take place. So let's say he starts
the other way. Fine, start the other way. Do ייבום yibum first
with her, right? And then do חליצה. chalitza. Now you can't do
another ייבום yibum with her, same story, right? Because it's doing, you
can't do ייבום yibum with both wives. Fine, but you know, but
do חליצה chalitza with her. Okay. But if he does חליצה chalitza
with her, then even though he did חליצה chalitza afterwards, it would
still go back and impact the status of this relationship because then
to continue to be sleeping with this wife after he's done חליצה
chalitza with one of the wives, right? It doesn't really matter what
order it is. After he's done חליצה chalitza if, if חליצה chalitza
has been done with, meaning, if this ייבום yibum was really the
stronger thing, then the חליצה chalitza would be meaningless. Normally you can
never have חליצה chalitza after ייבום yibum because after ייבום yibum there's
no meaning to חליצה. chalitza. But because we don't know which thing
has more weight, right, even after he's done ייבום, yibum, that might
not disqualify the or push off the table the act of חליצה
chalitza if this is the stronger relationship. So ייבום yibum with her
does not break this relationship. So therefore חליצה chalitza still possible and
חליצה chalitza is possible and necessary and חליצה chalitza takes place, and
therefore if this were the stronger relationship and חליצה chalitza took place,
you cannot go back and do ייבום yibum with her, right? So
you're really stuck.
Meaning he can't continue living with the חרשת.
chereshet. Living with her, right, because now he has, now he's dealing
with a wife, a co-wife of a woman that he did חליצה.
chalitza.
And why not do
חליצה chalitza to both of them? Because you can't do חליצה chalitza
with a חרשת. chereshet. Ah, yes. What do you mean by the
stronger? Meaning the,
we say there's different types of קידושין kiddushin and we're assuming one
is stronger than the other. Okay, that's sort of we introduced that
before about wondering about the different who was the husband. So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. כיצד תקנתם? keitzad takanasam? How are
you going to fix this? So אמר רב חסדא אמר רב, amar
Rav Chisda amar Rav, כונס
את החרשת ומוציאה בגט. kones es ha-chereshet u-motziah be-get. Marry the חרשת,
chereshet, meaning have sex with her, and then give her a גט.
get. Okay. So that was fine, that was ייבום yibum and then
a גט. get. Okay.
קטנה תמתין עד שתגדיל ותחלוץ. ktana tamtin ad she-tagdil ve-sachlotz. And then
do חליצה chalitza with the קטנה. ktana. So yes, you've חליצה's chalitza
off the table here, do ייבום. yibum. But and then do חליצה
chalitza with the קטנה. ktana. What was the only problem we said
with that? Is that after you've done חליצה chalitza with a קטנה,
ktana, he can't go and continue living with the גדולה. gdola. Wait,
wait, with the חרשת, chereshet, the גדולה. gdola. So don't go continue
living with the חרשת. chereshet. You want to just allow them to
go ahead and be free and to remarry. So do ייבום yibum
and give her a גט, get, and then go ahead and do
חליצה chalitza and everybody is done with. Okay.
And for the תיקון tikun is how to prevent עגונות. agunot. Yes,
exactly. Okay. To do ייבום yibum
he has to sleep with her.
He has to sleep with her.
Yep. And they don't consider any of the psychology behind.
Nope. Absolutely not. I mean you're right, it's like, oh, no problem,
you don't have to be עגונה, aguna, you just gotta sleep with
this man and he'll give you a גט get and then you'll
be
free. Okay. Exactly. Okay because once you do one you can't do
the other. The only thing you can't you can't have sex after
you've done one with one of them because it might be you
know the problematic situation of having already done יבום yibum. *yibbum* or
having done חליצה chalitza. *chalitzah* with one of the wives. So the
only thing is so you do the sex thing first and then
you give the גט Get. *get* whatever and then you get that
off the table and then you go and you do the חליצה
chalitza *chalitzah* and you're done with both. Okay so so now the
גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says like this. אמר רב Rav *Amar Rav* חליצה
chalitza *chalitzah* שמע מינה *shema mina* from that innocent statement which seemed
to be the only way of solving this problem we can infer
קסבר רב Rav *kasavar Rav* חרשת קנויה ומשויירת Cheresha knuya u-meshuyeret, *chereshet
kenuyah umeshuyeret* the relationship to the חרשת chereshet *chereshet* is a quasi
קידושין *kiddushin* okay קטנה קנויה ואינה קנויה Ktanah knuya v'eina knuya, *ketanah
kenuyah ve'einah kenuyah* and the קטנה ktana *ketanah* is either a hundred
percent or zero. You see Michael you would have said the opposite
right? Okay so the קטנה ktana, *ketanah* is either a hundred percent
or zero
and the חרשת chereshet, *chereshet* is a is a fifty percent. All
right? How do you hear that? How can you figure that out
from that little statement that רב Rav *Rav* made? So now it's
going to prove it to you in term by a counterfactual. די
סלקא דעתך *Di salka daitach* חרשת chereshet, קנויה ואינה קנויה *chereshet kenuyah
ve'eina kenuyah* if the חרשת chereshet. *chereshet* was the one that we
know that again you can look in רש"י *Rashi* to figure out
why I am not going to do it but we know that
one is one and one is the other. Just take it on
faith. רש"י *Rashi* shows you how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* knows that.
Okay? So we're saying the חרשת chereshet, *chereshet* is fifty percent and
the קטנה ktana *ketanah* is either all or nothing. And here we're
going to prove it by showing you what would result from the
counterfactual. די סלקא דעתך *Di salka daitach* חרשת chereshet? קנויה ואינה קנויה
*chereshet kenuyah ve'eina kenuyah* if the חרשת chereshet! *chereshet* was the ספק
safek. *safek* and קטנה ktana קנויה ומשויירת *ketanah kenuyah umeshuyeret* and the
קטנה ktana *ketanah* was the was the fifty percent. So חרשת chereshet.
אמאי קונה ומוציאה בגט *chereshet amai koneh umotzi'ah beget* why would you
have to do יבום yibum *yibbum* with the חרשת chereshet, *chereshet* and
then give her a גט Get. *get*? I have a better solution.
What would be the better solution? This is in the in the
counterfactual that חרשת chereshet. *chereshet* is the ספק *safek*. Okay we're going
to what will be the reality if the חרשת chereshet. *chereshet* is
the ספק *safek* and the קטנה ktana, *ketanah* is the fifty percent?
Okay we're saying the reverse but I'm going to show you that
רב Rav. *Rav's* solution or whoever solution was it? Whoever solution it
was רב Rav *Rav* רב Rav
*Rav's* solution assumed the opposite of this. Okay רב Rav *Rav's* solution
assumed קטנה ktana *ketanah* was the ספק *safek* and the חרשת chereshet
*chereshet* was the fifty percent. And here's how I'll show it to
you. Let's assume that the חרשת chereshet *chereshet* was the ספק *safek*
and קטנה ktana! *ketanah* was fifty percent. Why would he have to
do יבום yibum, *yibbum* and divorce her? There would be a better
solution. What would be the better solution? Let's take a look. Top
of ק"ד ע"א *kuf yod daled amud aleph* תשב גבי Teshev gabei!
ממה נפשך mima nafshach, *Teishev gabei mimah nafshach*
I skipped a line.
אמאי קונה ומוציאה בגט *Amai koneh umotzi'ah beget* why would he have
to do יבום yibum. *yibbum* and divorce her? תשב גבי ממה נפשך
*Teishev gabei mimah nafshach* let him stay married to the חרשת chereshet
*chereshet* to the deaf woman either way. Meaning do יבום yibum, *yibbum*
with the deaf woman and do חליצה chalitza *chalitzah* with the קטנה
ktana? *ketanah* and you should be fine. You don't have to give
a גט Get, *get* to the deaf woman. Why? אי קנויה היא
*Ee kenuyah hee* because if the חרשת chereshet? *chereshet* is a ספק
*safek* the חרשת chereshet, *chereshet* is either a hundred percent or zero.
Okay? So if that's the case right? Here's what he's going to
do. Do יבום yibum *yibbum* with the חרשת chereshet. *chereshet*. Either that's
יבום דאורייתא yibum d'oraisa, *yibbum d'oraita* and let's it's יבום דאורייתא yibum
d'oraisa, *yibbum d'oraita* then he does חליצה chalitza, *chalitzah* with the קטנה
ktana, *ketanah*.
Okay. Yeah he does יבום yibum דאורייתא d'oraisa *yibbum d'oraita* then he
shouldn't have to do anything.
But we don't know so he's gonna have to do חליצה chalitza
*chalitzah* with the קטנה ktana *ketanah*. So we're going to explore what
how it would play out. He does יבום yibum *yibbum* with her
and then חליצה chalitza *chalitzah* with a קטנה ktana. *ketanah*. So how
would that work out? If this was if she was totally קידושין
*kiddushin* and was a hundred percent then that's totally a יבום yibum
דאורייתא De'oraita *yibbum d'oraita* and the חליצה chalitza? *chalitzah* with the קטנה
ktana *ketanah* was meaningless and doesn't matter no harm no foul. If
this was zero percent if the חרשת Chareshet. *chereshet* was not married
at all then this wasn't an act of יבום yibum *yibbum*. This
woman was just some wasn't his brother's wife. She was really zero
percent married to her brother wasn't a brother's wife at all. So
if he wasn't brother's wife at all then doing חליצה Chalitzah *chalitzah*
with the קטנה ktana *ketanah* doesn't affect his relationship. Either way what
he does with the קטנה ktana *ketanah* won't affect his relationship to
the his
sister-in-law who is deaf. Either he was a hundred percent יבום yibum
*yibbum* and what he does with the קטנה ktana *ketanah* can't hurt
it or it wasn't יבום yibum *yibbum* at all and she wasn't
his sister-in-law at all and what he does with the קטנה ktana
*ketanah* can't hurt her. So there would be no need to give
a גט Get? *get* if the חרשת Chareshet *chereshet* was a hundred
percent or zero. Okay? תשב גבי ממה נפשך *Teishev gabei mimah nafshach*
let her just continue living with him either way. אי קנויה היא
*Ee kenuyah hee* if she was really a hundred percent married to
the brother הא קנויה היא *ha kenuyah hee* so then fine she
was a hundred percent married to the brother this is a hundred
percent יבום yibum *yibbum* and what he does with the חליצה Chalitzah
*chalitzah* with the קטנה ktana *ketanah* has no impact on it. Okay?
That's only a quasi-thing. ואי לא lo, קנויה היא *Ve'ee lo kenuyah
hee* and if she wasn't at all married to the brother it
was zero percent right? Then it's not a sister-in-law. הנך בי עלמא
היא *Hanach bei alma hee* it's just some strange woman. Okay? Not
a he's no not a sister-in-law at all. And חליצה Chalitzah. *chalitzah*
with a קטנה ktana, *ketanah* doesn't impact his relationship with this other
woman. Okay? וכי קטנה ktana *Veki ketanah*...
What? וכי תימא. V'chi teima, Okay, so that's why this doesn't work,
because if this worked, he wouldn't have to give a גט. Get
I mean, it could be the true, but obviously רבה Rabba is
not—I keep saying רבה—רב is not considering that, because then רב Rav
wouldn't have asked for a גט. Get. So it must be that
it's the opposite: that the חרשת Chareshet, is 50 percent and the
קטנה ktana is 100 or zero. Now we understand why you have
to give a גט, Get, because remember, with a חרשת, Chareshet the
only option is ביאה, bi'ah, right? It's got to start with ביאה
bi'ah with a חרשת, Chareshet. because there's no חליצה. Chalitzah So he
has sex with a חרשת. Chareshet Now, why does he have to
give her a גט? Get.
Because... okay, because if he didn't give her a גט Get and
he stayed married to her, and then he went ahead and he
did חליצה Chalitzah with the קטנה, ktana so if the קטנה Ketana,
was zero percent, wasn't really his sister-in-law, then the חליצה Chalitzah would
be meaningless and it wouldn't affect his relationship with his wife, with
his quasi-wife here. But if the קטנה Ketana was 100 percent, then
he would have a real מצוה mitzvah of יבום. yibum The חליצה
Chalitzah, would be a real חליצה, Chalitzah. and that would then impact,
because this is—this is a real thing. It might be—it might be
a quasi-thing, but it's not in doubt.
There's a real—there's a real יבום yibum that took place here, a
quasi-יבום, yibum, but it's a יבום. yibum Okay? And if so, therefore,
the problem would be if this was—if he did this definite quasi-יבום,
Yibum
okay, and if the קטנה Ketana is 100 percent, then both of
them are his sisters-in-law, this one more, but both of them are,
and the חליצה Chalitzah, with one sister-in-law would ruin his יבום Yibum?
relationship with the other sister-in-law. And therefore he has to do יבום
Yibum and give her a גט. Get So that shows that רב
Rav who is saying do יבום Yibum and give a גט, Get,
says this is the quasi-one and therefore because it's quasi, it can't
be maintained once you do חליצה chalitzah. with the קטנה, Ketana, because
that might be a weightier one and a real one and that'll
undermine that. So that's why you do יבום Yibum and a גט.
Get. So let's keep reading a little bit more in the גמרא.
Gemara This is the easy part of today's דף. daf. וכי תימא,
and if you say: קטנה מאי תמתין עד שתחלוץ עד שתגדיל ותחלוץ?
ktana, mai tamtin ad she-tachalot, ad she-tagdil v-tachalot? Why should the קטנה
Ketana have to wait till she becomes an adult and do חליצה?
chalitzah תשב גבי! Why not just stay married to her? אי קנויה
היא הקנויה היא אי לא קנויה היא נכרית בעלמא היא. I k'nuya
hi, hak'nuya hi; i lo k'nuya hi, nochreisa b-alma hi. So he
says, "Wait a minute. But according to this scenario, I got a
solution—I got a different solution than רב. Rav You're right. If he
does יבום Yibbum, with the—with the חרשת, Chareshet he has to give
a גט Get. for the reason we said. But why go ahead
and bother with the חרשת? Chareshet. Just go ahead and do יבום
Yibbum. with the קטנה! Ketana Either that'll be a total דאורייתא de-oraita,
יבום Yibbum because it's 100 percent the wife, or it'll be a
meaningless act because it's not his sister-in-law at all. Okay? So why
not just do יבום Yibbum with the קטנה?" Ketana? So the answer
is, "Sure, he could do יבום Yibbum with the קטנה, Ketana but
who are we forgetting about? The חרשת!" Chareshet Right? That's sure. There's
no problem in this scenario that the קטנה Ketana is zero or
100 to do יבום Yibbum with the קטנה. Ketana The problem is
that you're abandoning the חרשת. chereshet And if you want to worry
about the חרשת, chereshet and that is going to be something that
can only work by having sex and only work by doing יבום,
Yibbum and you're going to have to start with the חרשת. chereshet
Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says, "אם כן חרשת במאי תיפוק?" No,
im kein, chereshet b'mai tipok? Yeah, you could say that, but then
you haven't helped the חרשת. chereshet Okay, so רב—so Rav רב Rav
who is saying do יבום Yibbum with the חרשת chereshet. and then
give her a גט Get and then go on to the קטנה
Ketana is assuming that the חרשת chereshet is a quasi-relationship
and the קטנה ketanah is either 100 or zero. All right, now
the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet,
said רב Rav
ששת—רב must have been sleeping when he said that—הכי
נמי מסתברא hachi nami mistavra to be sleeping when you said that.
הכי נמי מסתברא, Hachi nami mistavra, that also makes sense. תדע דקמתריץ
רב חסדא אליבא דרב, Tedei d'kamitaretz Rav Chisda aliba d'Rav, like as
רב חסדא Rav Chisda explained according to רב Rav that, you know,
what do you call—that about—that this is the solution and it's based
on the idea that the חרשת chereshet. is quasi
and the קטנה ketanah, is a ספק. How do I—what makes me
say that that's the difference between the marriage to the קטנה ketanah
and the marriage to the חרשת? Cheresha. דתניא, D'tanya, we taught in
a
ברייתא: braita: שני אחים נשואים שתי אחיות יתומות, shnei achim nesuyim shtei
achayot yetomot,
two brothers married to two sisters, orphan, although one of them doesn't
have to be an orphan as we'll see. קטנה וחרשת, Ktana v'chereshet,
the real point is a קטנה ketanah and a חרשת, Cheresha a
קטנה ketanah where it's only rabbinic because she doesn't have a father.
So two brothers married to two sisters—we've had this case before on
the previous דף, daf, but on the previous דף daf they were
the same plane; they were both חרשות, charashot, right? Here they're at
different planes. Two brothers married to two sisters, one is married to
a קטנה, ketanah the other is married to a
חרשת. Cheresha, מת בעל הקטנה, Meit ba'al haktana, and the husband of
the קטנה ketanah dies.
חרשת יוצאה בגט. Chereshet yotza b'get. הקטנה תמתין עד שתגדיל ותחלוץ. Haktana
tamtin ad shetagdil v-tachalot. Okay, so now let's demonstrate this.
Couldn't this whole thing be solved if the קטנה ketanah does
מיאון? mi'un? Yeah,
and then you wouldn't have all this problem.
That is correct. And why didn't the חכמים Chachamim just say, like,
force her, cajole her to do מיאון? mi'un? So you are right.
So the גמרא Gemara is going to end the discussion by saying,
we're reminding us that we פוסקין pasken like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
that we tell the קטנה ketanah to do מיאון. mi'un. Okay, so
you are right. So the גמרא Gemara ends. All these cases that
could work. Okay, so here you've got your ראובן Reuven and שמעון.
Shimon.
Oh, but then we wouldn't have these fun mind games.
I didn't say that. That was Michael. Okay.
All right. Shh. We have ראובן Reuven and שמעון. Shimon. Okay, one
of them is married to a קטנה, ketanah
and one of them is married to a חרשת. Cheresha
All right, so fine. Now, okay, they're both דרבנן, Derabbanan, but they're
דרבנן Derabbanan of a different quality. Okay? Okay, and now what's going
to happen? So let's take a look. מת, Mes, where are we?
מת בעלה של קטנה. Mes ba'alah shel Ketana.
So the husband of the קטנה ketanah. died. So now he's got
a מצוה Mitzvah of יבום Yibbum or חליצה chalitzah. with her. What's
he going to do? So that's not a problem, because the קטנה
Ktanah, can do חליצה chalitza. when she grows up, at least. Okay?
So מת בעלה של קטנה, Mes ba'alah shel Ketana, חרשת יוצאת בגט
וקטנה
תמתין עד שתגדיל ותחלוץ.
Chareshet yotzet beget veketana tamtin ad
shetagdil vetachlotz.
So he has to divorce his wife. He has to divorce his
wife and then she has to do חליצה. chalitza? Why does he
have to divorce his wife? Any thought why he has to divorce
his wife?
Because אחות... Achos... he may have more of an obligation towards that
other one.
Exactly. They're sisters. So listen, if they were on the same plane,
they were both חרשות Chareshot or both קטנות, Ketanot, she'd walk away
because it's אחות אשתו. Achos Ishto. But because on different planes, you
don't know, and maybe the obligation to the sister-in-law, who's also sister-in-law
two ways, also your wife's sister, right, that maybe is stronger. She
can't just walk away. Okay, so why not just do חליצה chalitza?
with her and have her walk away that way? Because if he
did חליצה chalitza. with her, why can't he continue to live with
his wife? אחות חלוצתו. Achos Chalutzaso.
Everybody with me here? Right. So this is a case where she
can't just walk away, his obligation to her might be stronger, doing
חליצה chalitza. doesn't suffice. Okay, so now why can't he just divorce...
and once he does חליצה, chalitza. he can't live with her, why
can't he divorce his wife and then do יבום? Yibbum Right, because
then it's אחות גרושתו, Achos Gerushaso, אחות אשתו. Achos Ishto. So he's
got to sever the relationship with both. Okay. So what does he
do? חרשת יוצאת בגט וקטנה תמתין עד שתגדיל ותחלוץ. Chareshet yotzet beget
veketana tamtin ad shetagdil vetachlotz.
Now, מת בעלה של חרשת. Mes ba'alah shel Chareshet. That was the
easy case. Now the husband of the חרשת Cheresha, dies. Okay, why
is this more complicated? Same issue, you can't wind up... you've got
to sever the relationship with both, right, because they're sisters and one
might be stronger. The only problem is that she's a חרשת, Cheresha
so what can you not do with her? חליצה. chalitza So what
are you going to do? I mean, if he divorces his wife
first, he still can't do יבום Yibbum and then give a גט,
get because the act of sex will be forbidden because it'll be
אחות אשתו, Achos Ishto, right? So we're stuck. So in that case,
מת בעלה
של חרשת,
Mes ba'alah
shel Chareshet, קטנה יוצאת בגט. Ketana yotzet beget.
He has to divorce the קטנה, Ktanah okay, because it could be
אחות זקוקתו, Achos Zikukaso, וחרשת אסורה לו לעולם. vechareshet asurah lo le'olam.
And the חרשת Cheresha has no solution, he can't have sex with
her, can't do חליצה, chalitza. totally stuck.
Wait,
so can he just keep her as a boarder for the rest
of her life?
I don't know. Now let's say he had sex. He wasn't supposed
to, but he went ahead and he slept with the חרשת. chershet
Okay? He slept with the woman. So that is now... he wasn't
supposed to, it was אחות אשתו, Achos Ishto, but it was also
an act... if this obligation... if this was the stronger obligation, then
that was an act of יבום Yibbum. and now he can give
her a גט. get Okay? ואם בא על החרשת נותן לה גט
והותרה. Ve'im ba al hachareshet nosen lah get vehutrah. All right, so
that's the ברייתא. Braita. בדיעבד Bedi'avad it works.
Right, right, all right, fine. Yeah, okay. אי אמרת בשלמא.
Iy
amarta bishlama.
Now this is going to prove our assertion that it's the חרשת
chershet. that is the fifty percent and the קטנה Ktanah that's the
all or nothing. Let's take a look how it's going to prove.
אי
אמרת בשלמא, Iy amarta bishlama, if you said it's
good, חרשת קנויה משויירת קטנה קנויה ואינה קנויה. Chareshet kenuya mishu'eret Ketana
kenuya ve'eina kenuya. The חרשת chershet is the fifty percent and the
קטנה Ktanah is the all or nothing. משום הכי, Mishum hachi, that's
why דכי בא על החרשת נותן לה גט והותרה. deki ba al
hachareshet nosen lah get vehutrah. That's why בדיעבד bedi'avad he slept with
the
deaf sister-in-law, he can go ahead and then give her a גט.
get. Why? דאמרת ממה נפשך. Di'marta mimah nafshach. Let's play it out.
אי קטנה קנויה היא הנפקא משום אחות אשתו. Iy Ketana kenuya hi
hanafka mishum achos ishto. If, okay, let's play it out. He's going
to have sex with the חרשת. chershet What is the relationship to
the קטנה? Ktanah. Okay, everybody with me here? We're going to assume
this scenario, חרשת chershet, is quasi, קטנה Ktanah. is all or nothing.
If the קטנה Ktanah is a hundred percent, okay, then who then
is his sister... his sister-in-law is אחות אשתו דאורייתא, Achos Ishto de'oraisa,
no מצוה Mitzvah of יבום Yibbum. and she could walk away. If
we knew the קטנה Ktanah was a hundred percent, then she could
walk away because it would be wife's sister. Everybody with me? Yes?
Okay, and then give her a גט get is...
yeah, but then you know she's free anyway. If the קטנה Ktanah
was zero percent, then... ייבום yibbum was totally acceptable and a גט
get totally works. So either you didn't need to do anything with
her, she could have walked away anyway if we had known, or
the קטנה Ktanah didn't get in the way because he wasn't married
to her at all and therefore the ייבום yibbum and the גט
get will work. That's fine with this way. Okay, so that's what
it says. דכי בא לחלץ נותן
לה גט והותרה.
de-chi ba le-chaleitz
nosein lah get ve-hutterah. ממה נפשך, אי קטנה קנויה היא, ei ketanah
kenuyah hee, if he was 100% married to his wife, the קטנה,
Ktanah. הנך דאיתסרו משום אחות אשה, hanach de-is-as-ru mishum achos isha, then
his sister-in-law could have just walked away סתם, stam, so obviously she's
מותרת mutteres to somebody else now. Maybe he did an אסור assur
act of sex, but it doesn't change the fact that she's מותרת
mutteres to get married now. ואי לאו קנויה היא, ve-ei lav kenuyah
hee, and if he wasn't married to his wife at all, the
קטנה Ktanah was zero, שפיר מיבם, shafir mi-yabem, it was a good
ייבום yibbum and a good גט. get, That works. But here's where
it won't work
if you reverse it.
אלא
אי אמרת דחרשת קנויה ואינה קנויה קטנה קנויה ומשויירת, ella ei amart
de-chereshet kenuyah ve-einah kenuyah ketanah kenuyah u-mishuyeres,
if you assume the counter-factual, that the חרשת chershet, is all or
nothing and the קטנה Ktanah is 50%, it won't work. כי בא
לחרשת אמאי נותן לה גט? ki ba le-chereshet amai nosein lah get?
Why can he give a גט get after he had sex with
his sister-in-law who is deaf? והותרה? ve-hutterah? הויה ליה ביאה פסולה וביאה
פסולה לא פטרה, havya leh biah pesulah ve-biah pesulah lo patrah,
because let's say it was the reverse. Let's say this was the
50% and this was the all or nothing. So if it was
nothing, then obviously she could walk away. The concern is that it
was 100%. So if it's 100%, he's got a מצוה mitzvah of
ייבום דאורייתא yibbum d'Oraisa with this woman, right? But that מצוה mitzvah
of ייבום דאורייתא yibbum d'Oraisa is a problematic ייבום. yibbum. Why is
it a problematic ייבום? yibbum? Because he at the same time is
quasi-married to her sister. So therefore that act of ייבום yibbum is
called a ביאה פסולה. biah pesulah.
He has
a 100% obligation of ייבום yibbum and it would not have been
a legitimate one because he has a definite 50% quasi-relationship
with her sister. But דרבנן, de-Rabbanan, the rabbinic laws are that if
it was a problematic ביאה, biah, we do not allow a גט
get afterwards. We say a problematic ייבום yibbum does not count as
a ייבום yibbum and she still requires חליצה. chalitza. And of course
חליצה chalitza isn't an option for her. Okay, so that's why we
can't, that again proves like רבא Rava that the חרשת chershet, is
the 50% and the קטנה Ktanah is the all or nothing. So
if the חרשת chershet, was all or nothing and this was 50%,
then this would be a definite relationship, quasi but definite, and therefore
the act of ביאה biah would never solve this problem. Okay.
So what does it mean ביאה פסולה? biah pesulah? It means conditions
within which the ביאה biah was effected don't like what it means
that...
so exactly what's defined as ביאה פסולה biah pesulah is a whole
discussion of רש"י תוספות, Rashi Tosafos, but here it's sufficient to know
that it was אסור assur to have sex because it was his
wife's sister.
And this is a קטנה Ktanah that was
נשואין nisu-in without a father, right. Okay, so that again proves
רבא. Rava. הא מני רב נחמיה היא, דאמר ביאה פסולה פוטרת. ha
meni Rav Nechemya hee de-amar biah pesulah poteres. No, there was a
רב נחמיה Rav Nechemya before, I'm sure we've all forgotten about him,
I forgot about him. There was a רב נחמיה Rav Nechemya that
says that even a ביאה פסולה, biah pesulah, once you did the
act of sex, it works, even if it was a problematic act
of sex, and you can go ahead and give a גט get.
afterwards, you don't need חליצה. chalitza So that's how it all works
out. So you can still maintain the opposite of רבא. Rava. You
can still maintain that the
חרשת chershet is the all or nothing and the קטנה Ktanah. is
the 50% and we can still explain this case even though it's
a ביאה פסולה. biah pesulah. All right, so we haven't 100% proved
רבא. Rava. Only 50%. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Right. Exactly. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. No. הא
מני רב נחמיה היא ha meni Rav Nechemya hee, דאמר ביאה פסולה
פוטרת. de-amar biah pesulah poteres. אי רב נחמיה אימא סיפא, ei Rav
Nechemya eima seifa, if it's רב נחמיה, Rav Nechemya, let's look at
the end of this ברייתא. braisa. מי שנשוי שתי יתומות קטנות. mi
she-nasui shtei yetomos ketanos. מי שנשוי שתי
יתומות, mi she-nasui shtei yetomos, two orphans, doesn't literally mean orphan, one
is an orphan, the other isn't, קטנה וחרשת, ketanah ve-chereshet, ומת. u-meis.
Okay, so now here's a different case.
He's married, one guy's married to two sisters, the קטנה Ktanah. and
the חרשת. He dies. Comes along the brother שמעון. Shimon. Okay, that's
the case essentially in our משנה mishnah that he's got a מצוה
mitzvah of ייבום yibbum but of different qualities with each one. Okay,
and what does he do? ומת ובא יבם על הקטנה וחזר ובא
על החרשת או שבא אחיו על החרשת.
u-meis u-va yabam al ha-ketanah
ve-chazar u-va al ha-chereshet o she-ba achiv al ha-chereshet.
So then basically there was sex with both women. Either he had
sex with the קטנה Ktanah, and the חרשת or he had sex
with the קטנה ktanah and another brother לוי Levi had sex with
the חרשת. That scenario number one, or the reverse.
I'm sorry. Did I skip a line? No. נאסרו שתיהן עליו. ne-esru
shteihen alav. We haven't gotten to the reverse. They both become forbidden
to him. So what happened? So he first had sex with the
קטנה. ktanah and then him, I mean, I'm not going to give
the brother cases, it's more or less the same, and then he
or another brother had sex with the חרשת. So he had sex
with the קטנה, ktanah that's יבום, Yibbum, right? Fine, he did יבום.
yibum, Then he had sex with the other wife. Okay, now why
does that make the קטנה ktanah. forbidden to him? I mean, this
wife is forbidden because he can't do יבום yibum, with both wives;
you can only do יבום yibum with one. Why does it make
this wife forbidden to him? Because remember, these are relationships of different
quality. So this יבום yibum might have been the real one, right?
And if this יבום yibum was the real one, the weightier one,
then that kicked this—then it kicked her out of the—out of the
game. And then he can't go on living with her because this
would now be the co-wife of the woman he did יבום yibbum
with. So since you don't know which is stronger, once he did
יבום yibbum. with her and he—and you don't know that's better. If
you knew that's better, she would leave. But it might be better.
So you're stuck, you don't know which one is better, you have
to divorce both of them. נשאו שתיהן עליו. Neshu shtayhem alav. Okay.
At least they won't be עגונה, Agunah, just divorce both of them
and then they'll be—exactly.
Okay, and we need to have these sisters over here, right? They're
not sisters.
Okay. They're not sisters.
They're not יבמות. Yevamot.
Right. They're not sisters. This guy was married to both of them.
No, but יתומות Yetomot
just means that they wouldn't—they don't have the status of בר דעת,
Bar da'at, it wasn't a דאורייתא d'oraisa. with—okay. Okay. So, okay. נשאו
שתיהן עליו, Neshu shtayhem alav, כיצד תקנתן? Keitzad takanatan? חרשת יוצאה בגט.
yotza be-get. So the חרשת, he gives a גט, get וקטנה v'Ktanah
תמתין עד שתגדיל ותחלוץ. tamtin ad she-tagdil ve-tachlotz. And the קטנה ktanah,
she waits and does חליצה. chalitza Now the question is, right, why
the קטנה ktanah does חליצה? chalitza.
Because why is she doing—hold on, why is she doing חליצה? Why
isn't he giving her a גט get also?
Why doesn't he give her a גט get. also?
He did יבום yibbum with the קטנה. ktanah Hold on a minute.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara is going to explain. Let's take a
look. The גמרא Gemara... is going to figure this out with the
קטנה. ktanah Let's take a look. אי אמרת בשלמא. Ei amart bishlama.
And that's going to figure out why that's the
הלכה. Halacha. חרשת קנויה ומשויירת, קטנה ktanah קנויה ואינה קנויה, ורבנן היא.
v'Rabanan hi. If it's not this whole רב נחמיה Rav Nechemia of
ביאה פסולה. Biah Pesulah. If it is the case of—like—for—like for that
other and it's basically like the way רב Rav. would have it.
ביאה פסולה Biah Pesulah would be a problem. And who is it
and what are we assuming? We're assuming that the חרשת is 50
percent and the קטנה ktanah is all or nothing. משום הכי תמתין
עד שתגדיל ותחלוץ. Mishum hachi tamtin ad she-tagdil ve-tachlotz. That's why she
has to do חליצה. That's why it's not just an issue of
a גט. get. Why not? עד שתחלוץ, Ad she-tachlotz, דלמא קדים ובעל
חרשת ברישא, Dilma kadim u-ba'al cheresha be-reisha, והויא לה ביאה דקטנה ביאה
פסולה. v'havya lah biah de-Ktanah biah pesulah. Okay, so here's what it's
saying. Take a look. Okay, we understand why the חרשת, it was
a יבום yibbum and then a גט get. and that's fine. But
here's why by the קטנה ktanah a גט get? won't suffice. In
this case where the קטנה ktanah was first and the חרשת was
second, you really are okay within רב's Rav, schema. Why? Because the
קטנה Ktanah was either 100 percent, and therefore this ביאה biah was
meaningless, so he can still go on living with the קטנה.
ktana, So the ביאה biah was meaningless potentially? What?
It was אסור assur but meaningless. Or the קטנה ktana wasn't even
his sister-in-law, it was 0 percent, and therefore this ביאה biah also
had no implications. So actually according to רב's Rav approach—wait, if
it was—I'm sorry, you said the קטנה ktana might not have been
a sister-in-law,
so that means it was יבום with the חרשת then? Yeah, but
he could go on living with the קטנה ktana, because it wasn't—she's
not relevant to the—to the situation. If it was 0 percent, she's
just some סתם stam woman.
He was never married to her.
He was never married to her. No מצוות יבום. mitzvat yibbum. Okay.
So given רב's Rav idea that a קטנה ktana is all or
nothing, actually when it's this order, you're actually totally fine, in principle,
to go on living with the קטנה. ktana. You understand why? Either
it was 100 percent and this act wasn't meaningful, or it was
nothing and it's also—it's also irrelevant to יבום. But we're concerned
the other way around, and we're going to treat all—both cases as
the same because they're—because one will lead to the other. So if
it was the other way around, then within רב's Rav approach, this
was a definite 50 percent יבום. Exactly
50 percent. And then he went and had ביאה biah with קטנה.
ktana? So if she was not his sister-in-law at all, it wouldn't
matter. But let's say she was 100 percent his sister-in-law and there
was a מצוות יבום דאורייתא mitzvat yibbum de-oraita and he did it.
So that would not work. Why would it not work? Because it's
ביאה פסולה. biah pesulah. Since he's already definitely quasi-married to the—quasi-married to
the co-wife. That's true,
the difference between—doubtful—I—you gotta love it, the whole גמרא of the difference
between 50 percent or 100 percent or zero. So anyway, since he's
definitely married her to her, right, דרבנן, de-Rabanan, he is אסור assur
to have sex with her. And even if this is 100 percent
and this is a דאורייתא, d'oraisa he's אסור assur to have sex,
it's a co-wife, and it's a ביאה פסולה. biah pesulah. And a
ביאה פסולה biah pesulah would not—oh, solve the problem with a גט.
get. A ביאה פסולה, biah pesulah, you would still need to do
חליצה. It wouldn't count as a full יבום, you'd still need to
do חליצה. So within רב's approach, we understand why he has to
do חליצה with the קטנה, ktana why he can't give her
a גט.
get. Okay. Correct.
A ביאת פסולה bi'at pesulah does not count enough as a ייבום
yibum and therefore needs a חליצה. It will require it in either
order because one will lead to the next. Okay, so that works
according to רב. Wait, wait. So now we're good. We're still good.
If you assume ביאת פסולה, bi'at pesulah, you assume רב, that makes
sense. But here's how it's not going to work if you introduce—if
you assume the opposite of רב and you introduce רב נחמיה. Rav
Nechemia. Okay. אלא אי אמרת רב נחמיה היא. Ela ee amart Rav
Nechemia hee.
If you say it's רב נחמיה Rav Nechemia and he was introduced
to say it was the opposite, that the קטנה ktana was the
quasi and the חרשת was the all or nothing. So אי אמרת
רב נחמיה היא, ee amart Rav Nechemia hee, ביאת
פסולה... bi'at pesulah... who says... האמר ביאת פסולה פוטרה. ha-amar bi'at pesulah
potrah. פוטרה. Potrah. Then there's no explanation of why the קטנה ktana
would need to do חליצה. Because if it's רב נחמיה, Rav Nechemia,
right, the קטנה ktana either
had the... what... היבם יבא עליה ha-yavam yavo aleha with the קטנה.
So it was a ייבום, yibum, right? And even if it was
a scenario on which he was already whatever maybe married to the
other wife, רב נחמיה Rav Nechemia says I don't care, once you've
done a ביאה, bi'ah, even a ביאת פסולה, bi'at pesulah, it counts,
and give a גט. get. So because this ברייתא braita says that
he's going to have to do חליצה with the קטנה, the only
explanation of חליצה with the קטנה is is that it was a
ביאת פסולה. bi'at pesulah. And the only scenario that it was a
ביאת פסולה bi'at pesulah for the קטנה was that he was 50%
married to the חרשת. Okay? So all of this proves רב that
there is a problem of ביאת פסולה bi'at pesulah and that the
basic thing is that the חרשת is 50% and the קטנה is
all or nothing. Okay? So אלא אי אמרת רב נחמיה היא, שמע
מינה, אלא שמע מינה רבנן היא, שמע מינה.
Ela ee amart Rav Nechemia hee,
shma mina, ela shma mina rabanan hee, shma mina.
Thank God. Okay. So
you don't know how long that took me to sort of prepare
that last night, especially since I was falling asleep while I was
trying to figure this one out. Anyway, so we have resolved that
רב is correct, that the קטנה is all or nothing and the
חרשת is 50%. We're getting to the משנה. mishna. Okay, maybe we're
even going to turn the page.
רישא reisha and the משנה. mishna.
That... just wait.
אמר רב אשי,
Amar Rav Ashi, מרישא נמי שמע מינה. me-reisha nami shma mina. רבנן
היא. Rabanan hee.
You could have even figured it out from the רישא reisha that
it's the רבנן rabanan and not רב נחמיה. Rav Nechemia. דקתני, De-tani,
אם בעל החרשת נותן לה גט והותרה. im ba'al ha-chershet noten la
get ve-hutra. Right?
Remember that? Where he wasn't supposed to sleep with the wife that
was the חרשת, but if he did then he can give her
a גט? get. Okay. People remember that? The case where we did
before, what was that, the case of the sisters? Okay. Remember the
case of the sisters? He wasn't supposed to sleep with the חרשת,
right? It was a case of his brother was married to his
wife's sister. He wasn't supposed to sleep with the חרשת, but if
he did he can give her a גט. get, והותרה. Ve-hutra. ולא
קתני אם בעל הקטנה נותן לה גט והותרה. Velo tani im ba'al
ha-ktanah noten la get ve-hutra.
Why didn't it give a similar case by having sex with the
קטנה in the flip case? When
and that he could give her... and he wasn't supposed to have
sex with the קטנה who was married to his brother because it
was his wife's sister and if he did then he could go
ahead and give her a גט. get, It didn't say that. So,
and why didn't it say that? It must be it didn't say
that because with the קטנה it would have been a ביאת פסולה
bi'at pesulah and it's רב נחמיה. Rav Nechemia. So he says no.
אם משום הא לא איריא. Im mishum ha lo irya. That's not
a good evidence. חרשת דלית לה תקנתא דהיתירא, קתני תקנתא דאיסורא. Chershet
de-leit la takanta de-heteira, tani takanta de-issura.
The חרשת, remember the case was that the חרשת there was no
solution for her? Wife's sister, no solution. So because there's no מותר
mutar solution, we're going to tell you what would be the אסור
assur solution. But it would still be a solution. So we're going
to discuss the scenario of having slept with her and giving her
a גט. get קטנה דאית לה תקנתא דהיתירא, לא קתני תקנתא
דאיסורא. Ktanah de-it la takanta de-heteira, lo tani takanta de-issura. קטנה that
there actually is a היתר heter way of solving this issue, right,
with the חליצה and whatever, we're not going to tell you there's
also an איסור issur way of solving it, ביאה bi'ah and a
גט. get, Okay. But it's not relevant to proving whether ביאת פסולה
bi'at pesulah does or does not work. Okay, now, David asked about
what about the מיאון? miun? That's coming up in the next משנה.
mishna. And guess what? We've already done half of the משניות mishnayot
that are coming up. We've already brought them into this סוגיא. sugya.
So hopefully the next few pages will sound very familiar. מי שהיה
נשוי לשתי יתומות קטנות ומת. Mi she-haya nasui lish-tei yetomot ktanot ve-met.
Does this sound familiar? Married to two women. ובא יבם על הראשונה
וחזר ובא על השנייה. U-va yavam al ha-rishonah ve-chazar u-va al ha-shniyah.
או שבא אחיו על השנייה. O she-ba achiv al ha-shniyah. Right? So
basically he was married to these two women and but they're of
but they're both of the same right, they're both of the same
category. So in that case, לא פסל את הראשונה. lo pasal et
ha-rishonah. The first one is completely worked, 100% ייבום yibum with the
first one, or within this world they're on equal footing, and therefore
whatever happens with the second one did not impact his legitimate ייבום
yibum with the first one. וכן בית חרשות קטנות Ve-chen beit chereshot
ktanot or if they're both חרשות chershot and again in the same
category. וכן בית חרשות. ve-chen beit chereshot. Same would be true of
two חרשות. chershot.
However, the more interesting case is when they're of a different quality.
קטנה וחרשת. Ktanah ve-chershet. And this is what we quoted before. בא
יבם על הקטנה וחזר ובא על החרשת. Ba yavam al ha-ktanah ve-chazar
u-va al ha-chershet. או שבא אחיו על החרשת. O she-ba achiv al
ha-chershet. So he had sex with one and the other or his
brother with the other. In that case, because of different qualities... You
don't know which is the more weighty and the other and which
is the quasi and which is whatever, פסל את הקטנה pasal et
haktana as we just described, after he had sex with the other
wife that ruined his relationship with the first, with the first sister-in-law.
בא יבם על החרשת, Ba yavam al hakharaishet, let's see you disagree.
Yeah. בא יבם על החרשת וחזר ובעל הקטנה, Ba yavam al hakharaishet
v'khazar uva'al haktana. now same would be if it was reversed. First
was sex with the deaf wife and then with the קטנה, או
שבא אחיו על הקטנה, o sheba achiv al haktana, פסל את החרשת,
pasal et hakharaishet, same story. Again, because one of them might be
stronger than the other and you don't know which is which, regardless
of the order, now you're stuck, cannot continue the relationship with either
wife. Okay, so good, we've already figured all of that out. Now
we're not going to, we're not going to do more about that
now. Where are we? בא יבם על החרשת וחזר ובעל החרשת או
שבא... לא פסל את הקטנה.. Ba yavam al hakharaishet v'khazar uva'al hakharaishet
o sheba... lo pasal et haktana. בא יבם על החרשת, Ba yavam
al hakharaishet is that where I'm up to? Yeah. בא יבם על
החרשת Ba yavam al hakharaishet, וחזר ובעל הפיקחת. v'khazar uva'al hapikachat. No,
no, I didn't. New case.
That's the fourth line. בא יבם על החרשת Ba yavam al hakharaishet
וחזר ובעל הקטנה.
v'khazar uva'al haktana, I don't know if I did that. I did
that. או שבא אחיו על הקטנה, o sheba achiv al haktana, פסל
את החרשת. pasal et hakharaishet. Now פיקחת וחרשת, pikachat v'kharaishet, that's where
I'm up to. Okay, sixth line, end of the sixth line. Let's
say they are of different qualities but one is clearly a stronger
relationship. His brother was married to an adult hearing woman and an
adult deaf woman. So the adult hearing woman is דאורייתא. d'oraisa That
clearly is stronger. In that case, okay, בא יבם על הפיקחת Ba
yavam al hapikachat if he first had sex with the hearing woman
and that's a hundred percent יבום דאורייתא, וחזר ובעל החרשת v'khazar uva'al
hakharaishet או שבא אחיו על החרשת, o sheba achiv al hakharaishet, and
then he or his brother had sex with the deaf woman, לא
פסל פיקחת. lo pasal pikachat. It didn't affect the relationship, the first
thing was a hundred percent effective. בא יבם על החרשת Ba yavam
al hakharaishet if first he had sex with the deaf sister-in-law, וחזר
ובעל הפיקחת v'khazar uva'al hapikachat and then he had sex with the
hearing sister-in-law, או שבא אחיו על הפיקחת o sheba achiv al hapikachat
or his brother did. That's a problem, because then came a stronger
act of יבום, דאורייתא act of יבום, and therefore it affected his
existing relationship with the first sister-in-law.
Why wouldn't it be a ביאה פסולה bia psula though?
פסל את החרשת. Pasal et hakharaishet. It might be a ביאה פסולה
bia psula that it would, that's a good point to say that
she doesn't leave with a גט, get, but that a ביאה פסולה
bia psula is a חומרא. chumra. It means she doesn't leave with
a גט, she needs also a חליצה. But
it certainly worked דאורייתא and now it ruined his relationship with the
first wife, with the first sister-in-law. גדולה קטנה Gedola ktana and the
same would be
true...
yeah, we'll worry about what he does. Okay, גדולה קטנה, gedola ktana,
let's say similar except rather than hearing and deaf, adult and minor.
Same story, one clearly works, one is more rabbinic. בא יבם על
הגדולה וחזר ובעל הקטנה Ba yavam al hagedola v'khazar uva'al haktana או
שבא אחיו על הקטנה. o sheba achiv al haktana. If he started,
if he first had sex with the adult one, a hundred percent
יבום דאורייתא, וחזר ובעל הקטנה v'khazar uva'al haktana and then he had
sex with the minor, לא פסל את הגדולה. lo pasal et hagedola.
It didn't affect his relationship, he was already a hundred percent binding,
nothing afterwards could undermine that. בא יבם על הקטנה Ba yavam al
haktana if he started with the minor, וחזר ובעל הגדולה v'khazar uva'al
hagedola and then he had sex with the adult wife, או שבא
אחיו על הגדולה. o sheba achiv al hagedola. So that, the second
thing actually was more binding than the first, and therefore undermines the
relationship of the first, because he's now has a more weighty relationship
with the second. In that case, פסל את הקטנה pasal et haktana
and the גמרא... רבי אלעזר אומר מלמדין את הקטנה שתמאן לו. Rabbi
Elazar omer melamdin et haktana shet'maein lo.
You know what the solution in all these cases when you've got
a קטנה is? Get the קטנה to do מיאון. miun. אמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי אלעזר. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel halacha
k'Rabbi Elazar. And that's the only line we focus on now because
thank God we've already dealt with most of what, most of the
real meat of this משנה. Mishna. So אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל
הלכה כרבי אלעזר. amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel halacha k'Rabbi Elazar. We
rule like רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. When there's a קטנה, you get
her to do מיאון. miun. וכן אמר רבי אלעזר האמורא הלכה כרבי
אלעזר התנא. V'khein amar Rabbi Elazar ha'Amora halacha k'Rabbi Elazar ha'Tana. וצריכא.
Utzricha. דאי איתמר בהא, De'i itmar b'ha,
you need to tell me two places. We said here we teach
the קטנה and we said way at the beginning of this מסכת
masechet that you teach the קטנה. In what case was that again?
What was the case again? Anybody remember the first case of teaching
the קטנה?
Oh,
that was... oh, yeah.
Hold on, what was the case? דף ק"ט עמוד א'. Daf kuf-tet
amud aleph. שני אחים נשואים לשתי
אחיות. Shenei
achim nesuim
l'shtei achayot.
Right, it was the case about a sister. So he had this
מצוה mitzvah of יבום whatever with the sister, I don't even remember.
Okay, but it was a case of sisters and you had to
solve it, so you solved it by doing the מיאון. miun. Okay,
right. So you need it both cases. אי איתמר בהא קמייתא באה
אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי אלעזר. Ei itmar b'ha kammaita ba amar Shmuel
halacha k'Rabbi Elazar. I would have said there he says we say
like רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, משום דלא קיימא מצות יבום mishum d'lo
kayma mitzvat yibum because there's no really a clear מצות יבום mitzvat
yibum there because you're dealing with a wife's sister. So if there's
a wife's sister, the קטנה is already pretty much out of, I
mean, if she's a hundred percent sister you wouldn't need to deal
with it, but because of this whole quasi thing she's like, you
know, he's in the picture. But because it's an aspect of her
being a wife's sister, she's not so much in the category of
יבום anyway, right? We have to deal with it because of the
complications of the situation, but she's not really in the category of
יבום because she's a wife's sister. So there we'll let her do
מיאון. miun. Okay, we say do מיאון. miun. משום דלא קיים מצות
יבום. mishum delo kiyam mitzvas yibbum. אבל בהא, aval b'ha, דקיים מצות
יבום. d'kayim mitzvas yibbum.
Here
where he is מקיים מצות יבום, mikayim mitzvas yibbum, first of all,
he's already slept with both women, he's been מקיים mikayim it, and
second of all, you know, with at least, you know, that there's,
it's not like a case of a sister. Both women are potential
for יבום here, right? It's just you can't do it with both
of them. But they're both in the category of יבום. In this
case,
אימא תרווייהו ליפקו בגיט, eima tarvaihu lipku b'get, maybe we don't encourage
a מיאון miun where the יבום took place. We'll acknowledge that and
we'll go ahead and we'll do a גט or whatever but we're
not going to encourage a מיאון. miun. ואי אשמעינן בהא משום דגדולה
רמיא קמיה, v'i ashmi'inan b'ha mishum d'gdola ramya kamei, if you had
said here we encourage the מיאון, miun, maybe—I'm sorry, the first point
was the מיאון miun already took place, if the—the ביאה. biah. In
our משנה mishna that he slept with both women and the ביאה
biah already took place, we're not going to now say do a
מיאון, miun, right? Now that you've already slept with the woman, just
give a גט, right?
You don't need to do a מיאון. miun.
I know, but meaning I would—I would have said you do מיאון
miun in one case if nothing happened yet. But here where he's—he's
already slept with the women, give them a גט, don't now introduce
מיאון. miun. That's why I would have said you couldn't have assumed
we פסקן pasken like רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer here. ואי אשמעינן בהא,
v'i ashmi'inan b'ha, and if we had paskened like רבי אליעזר Rebbi
Eliezer here, I jumped ahead and gave this reason earlier, if we
had paskened like רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer here, בהא משום דגדולה רמיא
קמיה, b'ha mishum d'gdola ramya kamei, because here at least both women
are really in the פרשה parsha of יבום and the adult more,
and you want to get the קטנה out of the picture. So
therefore, there's a reason to sort of say the קטנה isn't really
part of this anyway, let's get her out of the picture. אבל
אידך, aval idach, but in the other case they were both legitimately
in the same פרשה, parsha, it was just a whole issue of—or
legitimately not, they were both an issue of sisters, so לא, I
might think that we don't encourage מיאון. miun. צריכא, tzricha, you need
both cases. Anyway, the פשט pshat of it is, is that according—you—with
רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer, when there's a קטנה involved, you do מיאון
miun and you tell her to do מיאון miun and that's how
you solve a lot of these cases. Okay, I have to tell
you, that was actually not bad at all in terms of getting
through that דף. daf.